A term that's popping up more and more
in the AI space right now is harness
engineering. It's the next big thing for
this year and just like context
engineering was for last year. And it is
really important, but just like context
engineering, it's starting to turn into
this buzzword that people are throwing
around without really knowing what it
means. And so that begs the question, is
this skill or even mindset, like I'll
get into in a little bit, worth learning
or adopting? And the answer is yes. And
so I want to get into that with you
today. Helping you understand what
harness engineering is. There are a
couple of layers to it that are really
worth knowing. And so I'm going to break
this down nice and simple for you in
less than 15 minutes. And of course,
like usual, I've got some examples and
demos to really make it concrete. All
right, so let's get right into it.
Harness engineering is all about
building the wrapper around the model.
So any agent is the combination of the
underlying large language model like GPT
or Claude, and then the wrapper around
it that gives it the context and defines
your processes. And so I'm mostly going
to be focusing on AI coding assistants
for this video, but really this idea of
harness engineering can be extrapolated
out to any agent that you build for
anything. And there are really two parts
of harness engineering. We have within
an individual AI coding assistant
session, and then we have really the
real evolution here that I'm more
focused on right now. This is combining
multiple coding agent sessions in a
larger workflow to handle a larger task.
And so we'll get there, but I want to
start more foundational here. And one
really important thing to understand is
that this first idea of harness
engineering within a single session, a
lot of the ideas here are very similar
to context engineering. This is a direct
evolution of context engineering. How do
we give the right ecosystem of context
to our coding agent? But there are some
important differences here that I want
to key in on. But first of all, I think
this diagram explains it really well. We
start with the underlying large language
model. This is the reasoning for our
agent. And then the first wrapper around
it is not something you build yourself.
It's actually the tool that you use, the
coding agent that you choose. And so,
Claude Code, Codex, Py, you name the
millions of coding agents out there. All
of them are actually harnesses that a
company has engineered around their
model. And so, this might not feel like
harness engineering cuz you're not
defining anything, but you're picking
the harness when you choose the tool.
Some people think Claude Code is the
best harness for coding. Some people
think Codex is. There's a lot of debate
right now. But, what's even more
important than the coding agent you pick
is the AI layer. This is the ultimate
wrapper around any coding agent session,
and this is what you get to actually
build. And so, when we think about what
goes into the AI layer, it's really
defining all of our contexts and
processes for our coding agent. So, our
global rules, our skills, and MCP
servers, all the capabilities we give,
code base searching like LSP or
knowledge graphs, our hooks, and our
sub-agents. Really like these six
components that are pretty much built
into every single AI coding assistant
now makes up your AI layer. So, no
matter how you want to inject your
process or your rules, you're going to
do it through one of these six things.
So, there are a couple of articles I
really want to lean into here to help
you understand harness engineering. I'll
link to them in the description. This
first one has an analogy that I want to
zoom in on here. I love this. So, on the
left-hand side, we have a representation
of what the model can do by itself, like
Claude or GPT. And spoiler, it's not
that much. We take for granted all of
the capabilities that AI coding
assistants like Claude Code and Codex
give to the model out of the box. An LLM
by itself, it doesn't have any way to
access a file system or Git or run any
commands. That's everything that comes
with that first harness layer built into
the tools that we download and use out
of the box. And so, that's what these
top bridges represent here. It's all of
the capabilities that these tools give
to the model to make it so it can really
act as an AI coding assistant, right?
It's the capabilities plus the system
prompt built into these tools. And then,
as we get to the lower bridges here,
this is where we start to get into that
higher-level AI layer where we get to
define things like the MCP servers we
use, the skills that we build or
incorporate, rules, things like that.
Even going down to Ralph loops, like
we'll talk about towards the end of this
video when we get into a stringing
multiple coding agent sessions together,
the ultimate kind of harness
engineering. So, stay tuned for that.
But, the point here is that each of
these bridges are tools that allow the
large language model to function and act
as an AI coding assistant. All right,
cool. So, with that definition, I now
want to address the elephant in the
room. The question you might be asking
yourself is, "Cole, isn't a lot of this
here just context engineering? Like, I
thought we were covering this in 2025."
And the answer is actually yes, to an
extent. And that's why I think that
harness engineering is becoming such a
buzzword right now. Most people don't
really understand how this is truly an
evolution from context engineering.
That's what I want to argue with you
right now. And so, there are two
important distinctions. So, first of
all, most of the harness around the
model, like this article outlines, it is
just context engineering. Your context
injection, your actions through tools
and MCPs, persistence, observability.
The one thing that really is different
is control, like Ralph loops,
orchestrating different coding agent
sessions and sub-agents. I think that is
a true evolution from sub-agents. And
so, we'll talk about that next. But, the
other really important distinction that
this article outlines is the skill issue
reframe. So, I alluded to at the start
of the video the fact that harness
engineering is not just a skill, it's
also a sort of a a mindset, right? A a
reframe. So, the author here says,
"There's a pattern I watch engineers
fall into. The agent does something
dumb, the engineer blames the model, and
the blame gets filed under wait for the
next version." As in, you know, Claude
screws up here, well, we better wait for
Opus 5. Or GPT messes up, let's wait for
GPT 6. And, you know, personally, I see
this all the time as well. I'm also
tempted to think this myself, and you
probably are as well. But, the harness
engineering mindset rejects that
default. And, by the way, I call this
system evolution. It's very in line with
something that I've been focusing on a
lot recently. So, here's what he says,
"The failure is usually legible. The
agent didn't know about a convention, so
you add it to agents.md. Or the agent
ran a destructive command, so you add a
hook that blocks it." Basically, the
idea here is every mistake becomes a
rule. Or the way I like to put it is
every mistake becomes an opportunity to
improve your harness, improving the
security through your hooks, your
processes through updating your skills,
anything in your harness, so that the
next coding agent session that issue you
encountered is less likely to come up.
And that is super powerful. That system
evolution means that you are taking
ownership and improving the performance
of your coding agent over time with the
AI layer that you control over the
coding assistant that you chose. And so,
really, harness engineering is all about
claiming that agency, taking ownership
of your system, so that when something
goes wrong, you're not just blaming your
AI coding assistant and feeling
helpless. Because things will come up.
Just like working with human developers,
there are going to be issues. But, we
need to make sure that we have a way to
learn from that and not just be at the
mercies of the next session not
encountering that problem again. We want
to be the human steering the system,
feeding forward. So, the initial
generation, we have our principles and
other kinds of context we feed in. And
then, we have our sensors for feedback,
our hooks, our review agents, the skills
that we give it for that
self-correction, evolving our AI layer
over time. The sponsor of today's video
is Google Cloud, specifically their new
agency CLI. And I'm excited for this
because nowadays it's optimal to build
your agents with other agents, right?
Using your AI coding assistants like
Cloud Code and Codex. Now, the easy part
is getting the idea for an agent, but
actually building it out and deploying
it to production, that is a different
beast. But Google has made this so
incredibly easy now with their agency
CLI. It's a collection of skills that I
can bring into my coding agent that give
it full, clear instructions on how to
build agents with the Google Agent SDK
and even deploy them to production and
monitor them. And so right here in my
Cloud Code, for example, I can say use
the agency CLI to build a research agent
that searches the web. Obviously, a
simple example, but it's going to use
the instructions to really help you
build any agent that you want. Then with
the help of the skills, your coding
agent will create all of the code. It's
one shot at a lot of different tests
that I've given it here. And then we
also have our local development
environment. We can spin up the agent
here so that we can test everything
locally with a full chat application
before we deploy our agent. And then
when you're ready to take your agent to
production, it is a single command to
deploy your Google Agent SDK agent to
the Google Cloud. Super easy. And your
agent gets its own identity in the
cloud. You have the playground here to
test it live, and you have traces, full
observability. So everything you need
for a production deployment, but it's
not extremely difficult to get all this
set up like it used to be. And the best
part is the agency CLI is free and open
source. You can take these skills, bring
it into any coding agent, and see how
easy it is right now to build any AI
agent. I'll have a link in the
description. I'd highly recommend
checking it out. So I also have this
companion repo for our video, giving you
a super concrete idea of what an AI
layer can look like. And this is a
really good representation, everything
here of the AI layer that I'll bring
into and evolve in each of my code
bases. I want to cover this quick before
we get into the last evolution of
Harness engineering, the really powerful
stuff, building workflows where we are
bringing together and orchestrating many
coding agent sessions. And I have
examples for that like with the Ralph
loop in this repo as well. And so I did
promise that this video is going to be
shorter, so I'm not going to dive
extremely deep into each one of the
components of the AI layer, but I do
have a video that I'll link to right
here where I cover in more detail the
rules and skills and LSP and hooks, each
one of the components. I want to stay
just really high level, give you some
golden nuggets here, and then you can of
course just give this repo to your
coding agent and have it help you
implement things and understand
everything here. So really the
foundation of your AI layer is all of
the rules, the constraints and
conventions that you want your coding
agent to follow, your patterns. And so
that's your global rules and any other
kinds of on-demand context that you have
as markdown, Confluence documents, that
kind of thing. And then your skills,
these are the workflows that you have
for your coding agent. Like here's how
you want it to plan, implement, and
validate. And I have a separate skill
for each because what I really want to
do, and I highly, highly recommend this,
is you want to do your planning,
implementation, and validation all in
separate coding agent sessions to keep
each one of them token efficient and
focused. [snorts] And so each one of
these skills is going to output some
kind of artifact so you can use it as a
handoff to the next session. And so this
is kind of getting into stringing coding
agent sessions together, but we're still
talking about doing this manually,
right? Like you'll run the plan and
you'll create the plan with the coding
agent with one skill.
And then you'll take this markdown and
then you'll give it to the next coding
agent session for the implement skill,
right? You go through that
systematically yourself. And so we'll
talk about in a little bit how we can
really bring all that together.
And then as far as hooks go, these are
honestly pretty underused. I love using
hooks for a few different things. First
of all for security. So a pre-tool use
hook. Basically, this is a piece of code
that's going to trigger before the
coding agent executes any tool call,
like writing out to a file, running any
kind of command. And so, this is where
we can build in security things like not
reading .env files cuz we really don't
want that in the LLM's context, or
removing directories in a very
destructive way, for example. I also
like having some kind of stop validation
hook. So, when the coding agent says
it's done with the implementation, I
want to deterministically run a set of
tests. Like, are the unit tests, the
linting, the type checking, is all that
really passing? Cuz if it's not, I want
to force the coding agent to iterate on
it until it is. And that's what this
hook does. And then, last but not least,
just running a quick lint after every
single file edit is really good just to
keep your code base nice and clean,
which also helps make your coding agents
more reliable in the future. So, there
you go. Just a couple of golden nuggets
for the AI layer that we have here. And
I even have instructions in the readme
for just running a super basic pivot.
This is the foundational approach to
agentic engineering. So, you plan with
the plan skill, just sending in the
feature that you want. You iterate on
the plan, you produce that markdown
document that you then hand off to the
implement skill in a separate coding
agent session. And you also have your
validation strategy for the agent to
check its own work in the markdown, as
well. So, feel free to try that out for
yourself. But, now finally, I want to
get to the peak evolution of harness
engineering. So, I'm going to jump back
to the diagram here. Let's talk about
orchestrating coding agent sessions.
This is when we can really scale the
amount of work that we get done with
coding agents. So, the main idea here is
you don't just want to take a massive
task or PRD and hand it to a single
coding agent session. It's not going to
be token efficient, and the underlying
large language model in the harness is
going to be completely overwhelmed. It
does not matter how good the AI layer is
that you created here, with things like
your skills and rules. If you send too
much into the LLM at once, it is going
to fall flat on its face. And so what
we're doing here, orchestrating many
coding agent sessions together, is we're
giving each coding agent a very focused
task. And so these can be sub-agents as
well, but like you'll see in the Ralph
loop, it's actual coding agent sessions
that are handing things off to each
other. So we can explore the
implementation that comes in from a user
requirement, have one agent that writes
the plan, send that plan artifact into
an implementation, and then for example,
this is just an example harness, but we
could have many code review agents
running in parallel. This one focuses on
security, this one correctness of the
implementation, and this one making sure
it's as simple as it can be. And then if
everything passes, you create the pull
request, otherwise you would iterate and
keep working on the implementation. And
you can do all this manually, like I was
talking about earlier. We can go to
Claude code once and create the plan,
and then open up another Claude code and
do the implementation, but the real
power with harness engineering here is
we can automate all of this. We can
create a system that automatically hooks
together all these coding agent sessions
with the handoff documents and creating
the pull request and everything like
that. And that's what the Ralph loop
does. So let's go back to our example
repo here. I want to show you what this
actually looks like. So the Ralph loop
is just one example of an agent harness,
but Jeffrey Huntley, the creator of
Ralph, he really is one of the pioneers
here. This is one of the first example
showing in a very basic sense how we can
automate stringing together many
instances of Claude code, CodeX. I mean,
you could do this with any coding
assistant because basically all it is,
I'm not going to get too technical here,
but I just want to show you a little
bit, is we have a simple script. This
can be a Python script, it can be a bash
script. I'm not going to go into the
code here, but essentially you give it a
larger scope of work, like a massive
PRD, and it's going to be responsible
for splitting that up into individual
tasks, and then running coding agent
sessions to handle them one at a time
until everything is done. And so you
give it a prompt. This is the user input
here. Like these are the different items
that I want to build in the spec, and
then it's going to produce a plan here.
This is the fixed plan. So, like this is
what it's going to do in iteration one
of the loop, iteration two, iteration
three. It's going to keep working, kind
of like build up a log as the different
Claude code sessions here are running.
And then, when it decides it's done,
it's going to produce some kind of
indicator of that. Like here I'm using a
done.text. And so, this is where it
decides like, all right, all eight spec
items from the original prompt are done.
We are satisfied. We can now exit the
loop. And that's the only condition, the
only way that we can exit the main while
loop here is if we have this done.text
and the coding agent is confident that
the implementation is done and all the
validation is there. And so, just trying
to show you a Ralph loop to give you one
example of a harness. But you can see
the idea here of we are using many
coding agent sessions to keep each one
very, very focused. But also, we're
automating it, so we don't have to baby
sit our coding agent as we're handling
these longer tasks. And this really is
the future of agentic engineering,
building these harnesses to handle
larger scopes of work as the models and
the underlying tools are getting more
powerful. Like this is the way. And so,
lean into this here. I mean, there's so
many resources out there for harness
engineering. And then there's Arkon, my
open source harness builder. Free to
use. This is the easiest way to get
started with agentic engineering,
building your own harnesses like the
Ralph loop, but more custom to you, your
exact process and software development
life cycle. So, I'd highly recommend
checking this out. Otherwise, I hope
this video was helpful for you in
general, just understanding what is
harness engineering, what's the fluff,
what's really worth knowing. If you
found this useful in any way, I would
really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next video.